# Fernando da Silva

#### DATA SCIENTIST

Florianópolis SC, Brazil

■ fernando@fortietwo.com | ♠ fortietwo.com | ♠ schoulten | ♠ schoulten

## About me

I am a data scientist specialized in economics and finance. I have 4+ years of experience working with data, time series models, econometrics, machine learning, ETL process, EDA and visualization, including reports and dashboards. I have 3+ years of real-world experience implementing projects and developing products using R, Python, Git, and GitHub.

I am curious, adaptable, and focused. I am always open to new challenges and I really enjoy creating new things.

# Work experience \_\_\_\_\_

#### **Análise Macro**

Data Scientist

May 2021 - Present · 1 yr 9 mos

- Development of predictive models using statistics, econometrics and machine learning for 13 Brazilian macroeconomic variables;
- Development, deployment, and monitoring of 4 time series predictive models;
- Development of reports and dashboards using Quarto, R Markdown, Shiny, and Plotly Dash;
- Development of R packages and release of the nucleos package for core inflation analysis;
- Development of ETL processes working with larger-than-memory datasets using R, Python, and SQL;
- · Development of web scraping for various static and dynamic pages using R, RSelenium, httr2, and others;
- · Macroeconomic analysis of Brazilian data using macroeconomic models such as the IS curve, Phillips curve, and Taylor rule;
- Time series analysis using EDA, decomposition, filters, autocorrelation, seasonality, stationarity, cointegration, Box-Jenkins methodology, univariate and multivariate models, and forecasting;
- Classes and courses on predictive models, econometrics, forecasting, macroeconomics, time series analysis, dashboards, reports, programming with R, Python, SQL, and others.

#### **Banrisul**

INTERN Jan 2018 - Dec 2019  $\cdot$  1 yr 11 mos

- Risk analysis and credit granting for SME portfolio (credit operations, personal/real guarantees, registration, provisions, etc.);
- Investment and application advice (fixed income securities, investments/redemptions, simulations);
- Customer service and sale of financial products (individual/corporate registration, account opening, aggregation of cross-sell products).

## Education

#### Federal University of Rio Grande (FURG)

Bachelon's in Economics Mar 2014 - Dec 2019

#### Federal Institute of Mato Grosso (IFMT)

ASSOCIATE'S IN INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY

Jul 2009 - Jan 2011

### Portfolio\_

2017

**meedr**: R client for the Central Bank of Brazil macroeconomic expectations data API.

https://fortietwo.com/meedr/

**Macro View**: Brazilian macroeconomic data dashboard developed in R. 2020

https://fortietwo.com/macroview/

**Macro Report**: Quarterly report on the analysis of Brazil's economic situation.

https://gecefurg.com.br/boletins/boletim-macro/

# **Volunteering**

#### **Economic Situation Study Group (GECE/FURG)**

MACROECONOMIC ANALYST

Crown on foundary loading management activities, accomomic data analysis, and content greations

- Sep 2017 Dec 2020 · 3 yrs 3 mos
- Group co-founder, leading management activities, economic data analysis, and content creation;
- Quarterly publication and presentation of economic situation reports, covering monetary policy;
- · Creation and automation of economic data reports and dashboards using the R language, Git, and GitHub.

#### **AIESEC**

VOLUNTEER STAFF Jan 2016 - Jan 2016 - Jan 2017 · 1 yr

• Business Development Ambassador (Aug 2016 - Jan 2017): development of the B2B area, partnership prospecting and spreading of engagement campaigns.

- Relationship Manager of Marketing (Jul 2016 Jan 2017): partnership prospecting with student organizations, alumni relationship building, event organization.
- Operations Manager of Talent Management (Jan 2016 Jun 2016): productivity and HR retention analysis by operation, identifying improvement gaps in sales teams, report compilation and presentation.

#### **Estudar Foundation**

**VOLUNTEER PARTNER**Nov 2015 - Oct 2017  $\cdot$  2 yrs

• The mission of the "Leadership 16h" volunteer is to enable the realization of the course in a larger volume and quality, reinforcing the mission of the Estudar Foundation to develop a transformative leadership throughout the country. As a Partner, I worked on the promotion, sale, logistics and infrastructure of two editions in Rio Grande RS, in the years of 2015 and 2017, where we were successful in enrollments.

# Skills

- R (4 years)
- Python (2 years)
- Quarto (1 year)
- Git (4 years)
- GitHub (4 years)
- SQL (1 year)

# **Languages** \_

- Portuguse (Native)
- English (Intermediate)